<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon against oppression and fraudulent dealing: preached at Paules Crosse, the eleuenth of December, by Charles Richardson, preacher at Saint Katherines neare the Tower of London</title>
            <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121051</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856240</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856240</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21769</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10738)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21769)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1360:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon against oppression and fraudulent dealing: preached at Paules Crosse, the eleuenth of December, by Charles Richardson, preacher at Saint Katherines neare the Tower of London</title>
                  <author>Richardson, Charles, fl. 1612-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslowe for Ioseph Browne, and Thomas Harper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through and some pages stained.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21769:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21769:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON AGAINST OP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion and fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Dealing: PREACHED AT</hi> PAVLES CROSSE, the <hi>eleuenth of December,</hi> BY CHARLES RICHARDSON, Preacher at Saint KATHERINES neare <hi>the Tower of</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLESIASTES, CHAP. 5. VER. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If thou ſeeſt the oppreſſion of the poore, and violent peruerting of iudgement and iuſtice in a Prouince, maruel not at the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for he that is higher then the higheſt, regardeth, and there be higher then they.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>George Furſlowe</hi> for <hi>Ioſeph Browne,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Harper.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21769:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21769:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, Sir IVLIVS CAESAR</hi> Maſter of the Rolles, <hi>and one of his Maieſties moſt Honourable Priuie Counſell:</hi> Encreaſe of grace in this life, and eternall happineſſe in the life to come:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it pleaſed God to giue better approbation to this poore Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering of it, then I expected: I haue beene
<pb facs="tcp:21769:3"/>
earneſtly intreated ſince, by ſome of my good friends, to giue way that it might bee printed. And though I am not ignorant of mine own inability: yet becauſe I know that God can, and doth worke, as well by weake, as by greater meanes; I haue yeelded to their requeſt. I confeſſe it is written in a rude &amp; homely ſtile, and I doubt not, but the curious cenſurers of this age, who like nothing but that which is for their owne humors, will carpe &amp; cauill at the plaineneſſe of it: but my deſire was to make it appear, that as <hi>Barnard</hi> ſayeth, in the like caſe, I rather ſought <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> then <hi>Oſtentation.</hi> Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the meanes of that mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb facs="tcp:21769:3"/>
which I haue, is chiefly by your honourable fauour, I haue therefore preſumed to publiſh it vnder your Honours name. And howſoeuer there be nothing in it worthy your Honours contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation: yet I beſeech you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of it as a poore teſtimony of that dutiful affection which moſt deſeruedly I owe vnto you. The Lord bleſſe your Honour with increaſe of all ſauing graces, that you may long be a profitable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of his glory, both in the Church, and in the common wealth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all humble duety and ſeruice, <hi>C. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21769:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21769:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. THESSAL. 4.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>That no man oppreſſe and defraude his brother in any matter: for the Lord is the auenger of all ſuch, as wee haue tolde you before and teſtified.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hauing planted a Church at <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.1.2.3.4.5.15. &amp;c.</note> and being driuen from thence by ſome malicious enemies of the truth, hee made his abode for a while at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens:</hi> where vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding what troubles and perſecutions were rayſed vp againſt theſe new <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerts,</hi> out of his loue and care for their good,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 3.1.2.5</note> hee ſendeth <hi>Timotheus</hi> vnto them, to viſite and comfort them. And being certified by him, with what great patience and inuincible conſtancy they endured tribulation for the <hi>Gospels</hi> ſake,<note place="margin">Ver. 6.7. &amp;c.</note> becauſe hee could not come vnto them as hee deſired, hee writeth this Epiſtle, to confirme and eſtabliſh them in the preſent truth. Wherein, in the three former Chapters, he congratulateth with them for their <hi>faith, loue, patience, reuerence to the word,</hi> and other excellent graces, which God by his ſpirit had wrought in them, which gratulation he concludeth in the end of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21769:5"/>
the third Chapter with a gracious prayer in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe,<note place="margin">Ver. 12.13.</note> that God, which had begunne ſo good a worke in them, would ſtabliſh them in the ſame vnto the end. In the two next Chapters, he exhorteth them to holineſſe, and to a Chriſtian conuerſation: And that firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, that they ſhould not content themſelues with their good beginning,<note place="margin">Ver. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>but increaſe more and more, and labour to ſurpaſſe,</hi> and to goe beyond themſelues. Then more particularly, he deſcendeth to the parts of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and layeth downe certaine ſpeciall rules, the better to direct them how to runne in this Chriſtian courſe. The firſt reſpecteth euery mans owne perſon in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate carryage of himſelfe. Namely, <hi>This is the will of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 3.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>euen your ſanctification, &amp;c.</hi> The ſecond reſpecteth a mans dealing with his neighbour, in this verſe that I haue read, <hi>That no man oppreſſe, &amp;c.</hi> For it is not enough for a man,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.22.</note> to liue ſoberly in regard of himſelfe, vnleſſe hee alſo liue righteouſly in reſpect of others. The words are imperfect in themſelues, and muſt bee ſupplyed out of the third verſe, in this manner. <hi>It is the will of God that no man oppreſſe &amp; defraud his brother, &amp;c.</hi> And this is the coherence that theſe wordes haue with the former.</p>
            <p>Now for our more orderly proceeding in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of them, wee haue to conſider two things in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. Firſt, the exhortation it ſelfe; and ſecondly, the reaſons whereby it is inforced. In the exhortation we may obſerue firſt the branches of it; ſecondly, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it. The branches are two. Firſt, that no man <hi>oppreſſe:</hi> ſecondly, that no man <hi>defraud his his brother.</hi> The firſt ſignifieth <hi>violence and manifeſt force:</hi> the ſecond, <hi>deceitfull and fraudulent dealing;</hi> and that by a generall conſent of the moſt interpreters. The extent is eyther in reſpect of the perſons oppreſſing and oppreſſed; <hi>no man his brother,</hi> of whatſoeuer place or condition he be; or in reſpect of the obiect, <hi>in any matter</hi> whatſoeuer,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21769:5"/>
great or ſmall. And howſoeuer theſe vniuerſal tearms be not expreſſed: yet the <hi>propoſition</hi> being indefinitely ſet downe, it is as much as if they were expreſſed. The reaſons are likewiſe two. The firſt is included in the word <hi>his brother,</hi> which (as we ſhall ſee afterward) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in it a very forcible argument. The ſecond is expreſſed, and it is taken from the vengeance of God. <hi>For the Lord is the auenger of all ſuch.</hi> And this is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amplified and confirmed by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> former teſtimony, in the laſt words, <hi>as wee haue tolde you before, and testified.</hi> And this is briefly the ſumme and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this portion of Scripture: Let vs now ſee the inſtructions that ariſe from thence for our further lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(That no man oppreſſe.)</hi> This is the firſt branch of the exhortation. The word here vſed in the <hi>Originall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> doth properly ſignifie, <hi>to goe vpon,</hi> or <hi>to climbe vpon</hi> a man, and to tread him vnder foot; repreſenting vnto vs thoſe perſons, who hauing oppreſſed a man by violence, doe trample vpon him. As wee read of <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> who hauing vanquiſhed thoſe fiue Kings of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> called the Captaines that were with him, and bad them, <hi>put their feet vpon their neckes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 10.24.</note> And to this purpoſe is that threatning denounced by <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28.43.</note> 
               <hi>The ſtranger that is with thee ſhal climbe vp aboue thee on high: and thou ſhalt come downe beneath ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry low.</hi> A plaine deſcription of that which is ſignified here. And the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God</hi> complaining of the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of her enemies, ſaith;<note place="margin">Pſal. 66.12.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt cauſed men to ride o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our heads.</hi> This is referred, as hath been ſaid, to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent oppreſſions, vvhen they that are mighty &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull, take boldneſſe to hurt and wrong thoſe that are vnder them. As the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>Doe not the rich oppreſſe you by tyranny? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence then wee obſerue in the firſt place,<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> that oppreſſion is a grieuous ſinne againſt the will of God.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21769:6"/>
The trueth of this will appeare vnto vs, if wee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how oft, &amp; how earneſtly the Lord forbiddeth it in the whole courſe of the <hi>ſcripturs.</hi> He chargeth the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leu 19.13. &amp; 25.17. Prou. 3.29.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not oppreſſe thy neighbor by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, neyther rob him.</hi> And again, <hi>Ye ſhall not oppreſſe one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> goeth yet further; <hi>Intend no hurt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>againſt thy neighbor, ſeeing he dwelleth ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by thee;</hi> thereby teaching vs, that we ſhould be ſo farre from doing and practiſing hurt to our neighbour, that wee muſt not ſo much as intend and deuiſe it in our thoughts.<note place="margin">&amp; 22.22.</note> And in another place; <hi>Robbe not the poore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is poore, neyther oppreſſe the afflicted in iudgement.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> maketh it a marke and property of a true member of the Church in this life, and of the kingdome of heauen in the life to come,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15, 3.</note> 
               <hi>that hee doth no euill to his neighbour.</hi> And our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> deliuering the ſumme of the <hi>Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.19.</note> ſetteth downe this for one branch of it; <hi>Doe no hurt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 3.14.</note> In a word, <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> chargeth <hi>Souldiers,</hi> who of all other men commonly take moſt liberty this way, that they ſhould <hi>doe violence to no man.</hi> Beſides, there are many reaſons to ſhew the hainouſneſſe of this ſinne. Firſt of all, it is againſt nature, for euery mans neighbour is <hi>his owne fleſh,</hi> as it were, Iſa. 58.7. Now as the Apoſtle ſayth, No man (vnleſſe hee bee a mad man) will offer vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to his owne fleſh; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.29. yea, the pooreſt &amp; meaneſt wretch in the world, beareth the ſame ſtampe and impreſſion of Gods Image that the greateſt dooth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.6. And therefore one man ſhould bee ſo farre from hurting of another, as that rather hee ſhould bee a <hi>God</hi> vnto him, as it were, to protect him, and defend him from wrong to the vttermoſt of his power. Hence is it, that there are ſuch titles giuen to Gods children, as ſhould put them in mind of that harmeleſnes that ought to bee in them. They are called <hi>Lambs, and Sheepe, and Doues. The Doue,</hi> ſaith <hi>Barnard,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Columba ſimplex eſt ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, felle caret, roſtro non laedit. Bern. in die purificat.</note> 
               <hi>is a ſimple crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it hath no gall, it ſtriketh not with the bill,</hi> as other raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21769:6"/>
foules doe: ſuch ſhould one man bee to another: But alas, wee ſee the common practiſe of moſt men is cleane contrary: The greateſt danger that befalleth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, commeth from whence it ought leaſt of all to come, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from man himſelfe. And now the olde Prouerbe is verified,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Homo homini lupus.</note> 
               <hi>One man is a Wolfe to another.</hi> Nay, there is no brute beaſt ſo hurtfull to man, as one man is to another: for they lightly neuer ſet vpon a man, vnleſſe neceſſity force them to it: eyther by hunger, or by feare they are conſtrained to fight. But one man taketh pleaſure to wrong and to hurt another, which cauſed <hi>Seneca</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the queſtion, and giue the anſwer;<note n="(b)" place="margin">Quid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini inimiciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum? Homo.</note> 
               <hi>What is the greatest enemy that man hath?</hi> Man himſelfe.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Caetera animantia in ſuo genere probè degunt, &amp;c. At homini plutima ex homine mala, Plin. in Prolog. lib. 7.</note> All other creatures, as <hi>Plinie</hi> noteth, do liue peaceably with thoſe of their own kind; they all hold together, and ſtand in oppoſition againſt all others. The Lions though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo fierce; doe not fight among themſelues: one ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent doth not ſting another; yea, the great fiſhes and monſters of the ſea deuoure none but thoſe that are of other kindes: But the greateſt euils that man ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, come from man.<note n="(d)" place="margin">O humanae malitiae dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanda crudeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas! Ferae par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt, aues paſcunt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes inſidiantur &amp; ſaeuiunt. Serm. 6.</note> This made <hi>Cyprian</hi> cry out with wonderment and admiration; <hi>O the deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cruelty of mans malice! the fierce Lyons doe spare Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el in the denne: the rauenous birdes doe feede Elias in the wilderneſſe: but one man exerciſeth cruelty vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is againſt that iuſtice, that ought to be in ciuill ſocieties, for the preſeruation whereof, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that men doe conuerſe ſafely together, &amp; without feare one of another. And therefore it was well ſaid by a wiſeman, that the firſt foundation of iuſtice is to hurt no body; and the ſecond, to procure the common benefit as much as lyeth in a mans power.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is againſt <hi>Christianity,</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Vita Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana eſt bene faciendi &amp; malè patiendi diſciplina. 1. Cor. 6.7.</note> which is a life that teacheth a man, to be ready to do well, and to ſuffer il, according to that ſpeech of the Apoſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Why rather
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21769:7"/>
ſuffer yee not wrong? Why rather ſuſtaine yee not harme?</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying that a Chriſtian man ſhould rather part with his owne right, then vſe the lawfull remedy of the lavv, to the ſcandall of the Church. Not that it is not lawfull for a man to proſecute and maintaine his own right; but to teach vs, that if hee will not doe this, much leſſe will hee ſpoyle and vniuſtly depriue another man of his right. And this was propheſied of long before, that in the time of the <hi>Goſpell, the Wolfe ſhall dwell with the Lambe, and the Leopard ſhall lie with the Kid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 11.6.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>and the Calfe, and the Lion, and the fat beast together, and a little childe ſhall leade them. And the Kow and the Beare ſhall feed: their young ones ſhall lie together: and the Lion ſhall eate ſtraw like the Bullocke. And the ſucking child ſhall play vpon the hole of the Aspe, and the weined child ſhall put his hand vpon the Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice hole.</hi> Thereby teaching vs, that though men by nature bee brutiſh and ſauage, like thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> that <hi>Plinie</hi> ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">Lib. 7. cap. 2.</note> who hauing copulation with wilde beaſts, doe beget a mixt and halfe wilde broode: yet when it pleaſeth God to conuert them, and place them in his Kingdome, they lay aſide their fierce diſpoſition, and liue peaceably one with another. For as it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the next verſe, <hi>None ſhall hurt nor deſtroy in all the mountaine of the Lords holineſſe.</hi> And in another place it is ſaid, that vnder the Kingdome of <hi>Chriſt, men ſhall breake their ſwords into mattockes or plow-ſhares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>and their ſpeares into ſithes, &amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay, thoſe weapons which before were inſtruments of cruelty, ſhall now be turned into inſtruments of peace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.10.</note>Fourthly, it is againſt the rule of <hi>Charity;</hi> for as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>Loue doth not euill to his neighbour.</hi> And in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>Loue reioyceth not in iniquity,</hi> and wrongfull dealing. And therefore, they that care not what iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry they offer to their poore brethren, are farre from that <hi>charity,</hi> that ought to be amongſt <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, it is odious to all good men, and maketh
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21769:7"/>
them many times weary of the world: As <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>I conſidered all the oppreſſions that are wrought vnder the Sunne, and behold the teares of the oppreſſed, and none com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth them: and on the ſide of their oppreſſors there was power, but they had no comforter. Wherefore, I prayſed the dead which are already dead, aboue the liuing which are yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue. And I account him better then them both, which hath not yet beene, who hath not ſeene the euill workes which are wrought vnder the Sunne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, it is <hi>theft,</hi> and worſe then <hi>theft,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. q. 66. art. 8.</note> as <hi>Thomas A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi> doth well determine; <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>theft</hi> are both of them (ſaith he) to bee accounted ſinnes, becauſe they both ſpoyle a man of his goods againſt his will: yet ſo, as in <hi>theft,</hi> a man is wronged ignorantly, that hee know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of it: but in <hi>oppreſſion,</hi> he is wronged by violence; he knoweth it, and looketh on, and cannot tell how to helpe it. Now that is more directly againſt a mans will, that is done by violence, then that which is done ignorantly. And therfore, <hi>oppreſſion</hi> is a more grieuous ſinne then <hi>theft.</hi> Againe (ſaith he) in oppreſſion, beſide the dammage done to the party, there is alwayes ſome indignity and reproch done to his perſon, which is farre worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fraud or deceit which is vſed in <hi>theft:</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Remota iuſtitia, quid ſunt reg na, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi magna larro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinia? De Ciuit. Dei. l. 4. c. 4.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto agreeth that ſaying of Saint <hi>Auguſtine; Take away iuſtice,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>and what are euen kingdomes</hi> themſelues, <hi>but great robberies?</hi> And hee relateth a ſtory of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Pirate, who being apprehended, and brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Alexander the great,</hi> when the King asked him, what hee meant to trouble the ſea in that manner, he replyed very ſtoutly and boldly; What doeſt thou meane to trouble the whole world? But, ſayeth hee, becauſe I doe it in a little Barke, I am called a <hi>Robber;</hi> and becauſe thou doeſt it with a great Army, thou art called an Emperor. Nay indeed, <hi>oppreſſion</hi> is farre more dangerous then ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>piracy</hi> by ſea, or <hi>robbing</hi> by land. For <hi>Pirates</hi> and <hi>robbers,</hi> being accounted as they are, common enemies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21769:8"/>
of all men,<note place="margin">Vrbani praedatores viuunt, &amp; viuunt, non ad deponendam, ſed ad confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandam audaciam.</note> whenſoeuer they are apprehended, they are hanged vp, or put to ſome other death. But theſe <hi>City robbers,</hi> as one calleth them, they domineir in gold and purple, <hi>and liue not to lay aſide, but to encreaſe their boldnes.</hi> And this made <hi>Diogenes</hi> laugh heartily, when he ſaw the <hi>Sherifes</hi> and other officers leade a poore thiefe to execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that had robbed the treaſurie;<note n="(a)" place="margin">Laert. in eius vita.</note> 
               <hi>Great theeues,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>leade little theeues to the Gallowes.</hi> The poore Snakes, that peraduenture for meere neceſſity breake a mans houſe, or otherwiſe pilfer his goods, they lie in priſon,<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.10.5.</note> 
               <hi>fast bound in miſery and yron, both hungry and thirſty, their ſoules fainting in them,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayeth. But theſe mighty <hi>oppreſſors,</hi> who are the greateſt theeues of all, they <hi>stretch themſelues vpon their beds of yuorie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos, 6.4. Luc. 16.19.</note> and with the <hi>rich glutton,</hi> are <hi>clothed in purple and fine linnen, &amp; fare delicately euery day.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 109.11.</note> And hence it is, that <hi>Dauid</hi> by the ſpirite of propheſie, curſing his enemies, amongſt other things, he ſayth, <hi>Let the extortioner catch all that he hath.</hi> As though a man could not be worſe plagued, then to fall into the handes of one of theſe mercileſſe <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, it is a degree of murder: according to that ſaying of <hi>Sirach; The bread of the needfull is the life of the poore:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 34.22.</note> 
               <hi>he that defraudeth him thereof, is a murderer.</hi> For a man to depriue the poore of that wherein his life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth, is all one with God, as to take away his life it ſelf. Nay <hi>Antisthenes</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> was wont to ſay, that <hi>oppreſſors</hi> were more hurtful them common <hi>hang-men;</hi> for the <hi>hang-man</hi> putteth to death none but malefactors: but <hi>oppreſſors</hi> ſpoyle &amp; vndoe them that are moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note>This doctrine then, to apply it to our times, doth ſerue for the iuſt reproofe of all oppreſſors whatſoeuer they be. <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> is a moſt filthy bottomleſſe ſinke of grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous enormities. <note place="margin">Lerna maloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> To rip vp all the kinds thereof were infinite: and therefore I will deale with ſome of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21769:8"/>
principall. There is <hi>oppreſſion</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and in the <hi>common-wealth.</hi> I know as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid wittily, It is not ſafe for a poore hare to preach ſuch doctrine to theſe Lions, hee ſhall haue much adoe to eſcape their pawes: But <hi>whatſoeuer the Lord commandeth me, that muſt I ſpeak,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>I muſt not be afraide of any of their forces, leſt hee deſtroy mee before them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, to beginne with the Church. There is oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there in thoſe <hi>ſacrilegious impropriations,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the liuings of the Church are alienated to other v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And this is a very great oppreſſion: for tythes and other reuenues were giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Church by our deuoute forefathers, for the maintenance of Gods worſhippe, &amp; of the Miniſtery of his Word; and therefore it is the more grieuous ſinne for any man to incroach vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">In iure fori, non in iure coeli. Aug. de vita &amp; morib. Cler.</note> I know they that holde them, pleade law for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. And howſoeuer their plea will hold in the court of men, yet it will not hold in the court of heauen. And yet ſuch is the iniquity of the times, that many couetous <hi>Patrones,</hi> euen where there is no <hi>impropriation,</hi> can finde meanes eyther by <hi>vnconſcionable Leaſes,</hi> or by <hi>ſequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to withhold the profites from the Church.</p>
            <p>But it is in vain to ſpend any longer time in ſpeaking to the <hi>belly that hath no eares.</hi> There is little hope euer to preuayle with ſuch perſons, vnleſſe it pleaſe the <hi>Lord</hi> to put into the hearts of godly Princes,<note place="margin">Nehem. 13.11.12.</note> with good <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> to compell them <hi>to bring their tythes againe into the houſe of God.</hi> VVhat a glorious worke would this bee for his <hi>Maieſty,</hi> and what a renowmed <hi>Parliament</hi> would that bee, wherein this thing might bee effected! And thus much for the firſt kind of <hi>oppreſſion</hi> that is in the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, there is <hi>oppreſſion</hi> alſo in the <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> and that eyther in <hi>priuate affaires,</hi> or in <hi>publike iudgement.</hi> For the firſt, It is an ordinary thing for mighty men, &amp; men of power, in their dealing to oppreſſe thoſe that are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21769:9"/>
vnder them. It is true, great men ſhould be to the poore people,<note place="margin">Iſa. 32 2. &amp; 14.6. Ezech. 22.29.</note> 
               <hi>as a ſhelter from the wind, and a couert from the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest.</hi> But for the moſt part, <hi>they ſmite the people in anger with a continuall plague, and rule them in wrath,</hi> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh of the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi> yea they <hi>violently oppreſſe the poore, and vexe the needy againſt right?</hi> There is no ſpectacle more pleaſant to their eyes, then the ruines of the poore. They are greater plagues and calamities to the places where they dwell, then an <hi>inundation</hi> or a <hi>fire:</hi> for, as the riuers, riſing at the firſt of ſmall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and afterwards being intolerably increaſed, do at the laſt with violence beare downe all before them, and carry it away: ſo theſe couetous great men, the more they increaſe, the more they oppreſſe, and make the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of the oppreſſed, as it were ſteppes to the oppreſſion of others. And as the fire, hauing ſeized firſt vpon one houſe, flyeth preſently to another, and from that to a third, till, if it bee not preuented, it lay all the ſtreet euen with the ground: ſo theſe perſons by cruell <hi>oppreſſion ioyn houſe to houſe, and land to land,</hi> till there bee nothing left for the poore, but lamentable <hi>deſolation:</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Nemo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes aggredi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutus poteſt. Sen. in Medea.</note> So that no man can ſafely conuerſe with, nor liue by thoſe that are mighty.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Noui ego iſtos Polypos, quicquid teti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerint tenent. Plaut. in Auſul. Gen. 10 9.</note> They are right <hi>Polypi,</hi> whatſoeuer they catch by hooke or by crooke, it is their owne. Theſe are the great <hi>Nimrods,</hi> the mighty <hi>hunters</hi> of the earth, that hunt the poore people as the wild beaſts doe their prey. Theſe are they, that count it their glory and felicity, to play the <hi>Termagaunts</hi> ouer the poore, &amp; to terrifie them with their power.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Peruerſa magnitudinis &amp; poteſtatis aeſtimatio eſt, iniurijs vires metiri. Sen. de Benef lib. 1. Iob. 24.10. &amp; 20.19.</note> But the very heathen man could teach them, that it is a bad eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a mans greatnes and power, to meaſure his ſtrength by the iniuries that hee is able to doe.</p>
            <p>But this ſinne is chiefly committed by cruell <hi>Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords;</hi> partly, by incloſing the Commons, and decaying tillage, whereby they <hi>take the gleaning from the hungry;</hi> yea, <hi>they vndoe many, and ſpoyle houſes which they builded not:</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21769:9"/>
ſo that a man may ſay of them, that whereſoeuer they come, <hi>deſolation and deſtruction are in their pathes;</hi> partly,<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.7.</note> by racking their rents, &amp; taking exceſſiue fines; &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by making their Leaſes voide at their pleaſure: for with theſe men<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pactum no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pactu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, non pactum pactu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, quod illis lubet, Plaut. in Aulul. Iſa. 3.15. Cic. in Verrem. lib. 4.</note> that which is couenant to day, ſhall be none to morrow, &amp; that which is now no couenant, ſhall bee a couenant when they liſt. By which kinde of dealing, <hi>they beat the poore to peeces, and miſerably grinde their faces.</hi> And to this purpoſe they haue their prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Bayliffes,</hi> and other <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who like <hi>bloud-hounds</hi> hunt about to finde out booties for them to ſeize vpon. The whole land groaneth vnder this burden. The Lord gaue a commandement in the <hi>Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 22.6.</note> that men ſhould not <hi>take nor kill the damme with her young:</hi> but theſe mercileſſe perſons, as much as in them lyeth, by theſe intolerable vexations, doe euen kill the poore mother with her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Now the cauſes of all theſe hard courſes, if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſire to know, are diuers. The firſt is <hi>ambition,</hi> when men hauing gotten a deale of wealth together, giue many hundreth pounds, to buy one degree of honour after another, to make themſelues great in the world, &amp; I know not how many thouſand poundes, to aduance their daughters in marriage, to make them Ladies or great perſonages. Then ſecondly, they muſt laſh it out, and flaunt it in all brauery of <hi>apparrell,</hi> that they may, at the leaſt, match them of their owne ranke. And when by theſe meanes they haue emptyed their cofers, they muſt coyne new money on their poore tenants skinnes. A third cauſe is <hi>ſumptuous building:</hi> It is one of the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this age, that euery man, of any degree, muſt build like Princes: As the Prophet ſayth,<note place="margin">Ier. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>They will build them great houſes, and large chambers, with great windowes, &amp; will ſiele them with Cedar, and paint them with vermilion.</hi> And then not onely their owne <hi>Tenants,</hi> but all the Country about them ſhall bee tyred out with carriages. Poore men are glad to toyle themſelues and their cattell, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21769:10"/>
in the deepe of winter, yea ſometimes in the midſt of harueſt, to bring timber or ſtones, or other prouiſion, and all for feare of a further diſpleaſure: for if any man refuſe to come at their call, they will bee ſure to ſit on his skirts, and to pay him home, eyther by rayſing him in the <hi>Subſidy,</hi> or by doubling his charge for the warres, or one way or other. But let them remember, what the <hi>Prophet</hi> denounceth againſt them,<note place="margin">Ver. 13.</note> in the place before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged: <hi>Woe be to him,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that buildeth his houſe by vnrighteouſneſſe, and his chambers without equity: hee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his neighbour without wages, and giueth him not for his worke.</hi> The laſt cauſe is <hi>exceſſiue feasting;</hi> wherein men are grown to ſuch exceeding riot, that neyther the land, nor the ſea, nor the aire is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to furniſh their tables, (though the poore get but little reliefe in many places for all this.<note place="margin">Mat. 20.12. Pſal. 127.2.</note>) The toiling <hi>Labourer,</hi> who endureth the <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and heate of the day,</hi> the poore <hi>huſbandman</hi> and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Tenant,</hi> that <hi>riſeth earely, and goeth late to bed,</hi> doth eate the <hi>bread of carefulneſſe,</hi> and ſitteth with many an hungry meale, his poore children peraduenture crying for food, and all to bring a full diet to his <hi>Landlords</hi> Table; As if theſe men were ſlaues and ſeruants, and not ſonnes. <hi>Iob</hi> had a better conceit of thoſe that were his ſeruants in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,<note place="margin">Iob. 31.15.</note> then theſe perſons haue of their <hi>Tenants. Hee that hath made mee in the wombe, hath he not made him?</hi> Theſe poore wretches, whom thou by thy cruell oppreſſion cauſeſt to toyle and moyle like drudges, or elſe they cannot liue; are the workemanſhippe of God as well as thou, and as deare to him as thou art, notwithſtanding all thy greatneſſe, and it may be, dearer.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, there is <hi>oppreſſion in iudgement.</hi> But dare this <hi>vgly monſter</hi> ſet her foule feete on the ſeat of <hi>Iuſtice?</hi> Surely, in the times of the <hi>Prophets</hi> &amp; <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſhe durſt; Elſe why,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.6.</note> ſayeth Saint <hi>Iames, Doe not the rich oppreſſe you by tyranny, and draw you before the iudgement ſeates?</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that a meanes of <hi>oppreſſion,</hi> which was ordained to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21769:10"/>
be a <hi>protection</hi> of the poore. And why doth <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.17.</note> that in his obſeruation hee hath ſeen <hi>a iuſt man periſh in his iuſtice?</hi> that though he had a iuſt cauſe, yet hee hath beene caſt in it.<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.23.</note> And this the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of in his time, that <hi>the Princes were rebellious, and companions of theeues; and that euery one loueth gifts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">&amp; 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>and followeth after rewards, &amp;c.</hi> And that whereas the <hi>Lord looked for iudgement, there was nothing but oppreſſion, and for righteouſnes, &amp; there was nothing but a crying.</hi> And the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Amos</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Amos. 5.7. &amp; 6.12.</note> that <hi>they had turned iudgement into worme-wood &amp; gall, and the fruit of righteouſnes into hemlocke.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Zephaniah</hi> is not afraid to affirme,<note place="margin">Zeph. 3.3.</note> that <hi>their Princes were as roaring Lions, and her Iudges as rauening Wolues.</hi> But it may bee, the times are better now: what then mean thoſe <hi>Prouerbs,</hi> that are ſo riſe amongſt vs? <hi>As a man is friended, ſo is his matter ended.</hi> And,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Cui vis eſt, ius non metuit, ius obruitur vi.</note> 
               <hi>might ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goeth right.</hi> As <hi>Aeſops wolfe</hi> ſaid to the ſheepe, when they were in contention; <hi>Thou haſt a better cauſe then I, but I haue ſtronger teeth then thou.</hi> And as the <hi>Orator</hi> ſaid of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pecunioſus damnari non poteſt.</note> 
               <hi>A money man can hardly be condemned,</hi> be his cauſe what it wil be. There were certain ſacred pictures in the court as <hi>Thebes,</hi> repreſenting the perſons of the <hi>Iudges,</hi> which were al made without hands, &amp; the chiefeſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted eyes alſo: wherby was ſignified that <hi>Iudges</hi> ſhould be free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bribes, &amp; void of partiality, that they ſhould be led neither by fauor nor affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect neither loue nor hatred in determining of cauſes, whether <hi>criminall</hi> or <hi>iudiciall.</hi> And let vs conceiue the beſt: Let vs take it for granted, that our Iudges are moſt incorrupt, and that, as <hi>Iustinian</hi> ſaid, they can lift vp their hands cleane, to God, to the King, and to the law; yet <hi>wrangling Lawyers,</hi> if they may haue their wils, will cauſe iudgement to bee peruerted. They will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſutes, as once ſaith,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Lites no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tantum luſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ſed &amp; ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lares facient.</note> not for diuers yeares onely, but for diuers ages; that if a man ſhould liue as long as <hi>Nestor</hi> did, and beginne a fute in his youth, hee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21769:11"/>
ſhould hardly make an ende of it in his olde age, nay, it is like, hee ſhould be conſtrained to leaue it to his heyre to finiſh; and this they doe, that they may enrich themſelues by ſpoyling their poore Clients. Is it not a grieuous <hi>oppreſſion,</hi> to cauſe a poore man to come trot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or trudging vp hither, from the furtheſt part of the land, Terme after Terme, and ſtill his cauſe as far from being ended, as it was at the firſt? he in the mean while, doth nothing but empty his purſe, by paying fees, firſt to one,<note place="margin">Mar. 5.26.</note> &amp; then to another. As it is ſaid of the woman in the <hi>Gospell,</hi> that had beene ſicke of <hi>an iſſue of bloud, twelue yeares,</hi> and had ſpent all that ſhee had vpon <hi>Phyſitians, &amp; yet it auayled her nothing,</hi> but ſhee beeame much worſe: So it fareth with moſt men that goe to law in theſe dayes:<note place="margin">A. Gell. lib. 5. cap. 1. Idem lib. 11. cap. 9.</note> for the <hi>Lawyer</hi> eyther with <hi>Protagoras,</hi> with gloſing ſpeeches will make the worſe cauſe ſeeme the better, or with <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> by mercenary ſilence, will betray the good cauſe, which he hath taken vpon him to defend; or with <hi>Penelope,</hi> as much as he hath brought the cauſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward one Terme, hee will bring as farre backe againe the next Terme: or will draw out the webbe of a ſuite ſo long, till the poore Client want weft to proſecute it; and ſo after all his labour and trauel, he muſt bee infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to let it fall; or if hee doe at the laſt recouer, and haue the matter goe on his ſide, yet he ſhall bee no great gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by the match; for as one ſayeth,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Maior eſt expenſarum ſumptus, quam ſententiae fructus. Aelian. l. 9. c. 18</note> the charges of the ſuite are greater, then the coſts that ſhall be awarded him. This made <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> ſay, that if a man ſhould ſhew him two wayes, one to hell, the other to the barre, hee would rather chuſe that that went to hell. I do not ſpeake, nor I haue not a thought to ſpeake againſt the vſe of the Law. I acknowledge it as neceſſary for the common wealth, as the ſunne is for the world:<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſt funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menrum liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, fons aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis. Cic. pro A. Cluent.</note> It is the <hi>foundation of liberty,</hi> the <hi>fountaine of equity;</hi> and as the body is without the ſoule, ſo would the commonwealth be without the Law.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eſt propug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naculum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, Cic. in L. Piſonem.</note> It is the very <hi>bulwarke</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21769:11"/>
of our ſafety;</hi> the eye whereof is <hi>Prudence,</hi> the hand <hi>Fortitude,</hi> the beauty <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and the foundation of it is laide in <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> And I doubt not, but there are many conſcionable Lawyers, who deale faithfully in the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes committed to their truſt. But I ſpeake againſt thoſe baſe &amp; degenerate profeſſors of the <hi>law,</hi> which are a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh and ſtaine to the reſt, and which, like <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ultures,</hi> doe nothing but gape after the prey. By all theſe meanes the poore people are grieuouſly oppreſſed. To which, I might adde our<note n="(d)" place="margin">Non miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura autem niſi plena cruoris hirudo. Horat. Pſal. 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>cutthroate vſurers, our bloud-ſucking brokers, our griping extortioners, which eate vp the people as they would eate bread:</hi> but the time would faile mee. And they haue beene ſo often cryed out vpon, both here and in other places, as there is now no hope of their reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They haue got them <hi>an whores forehead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier 3.3.</note> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſayth; <hi>they cannot be aſhamed.</hi> And thus much for the firſt branch of the exhortation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And defraud.)</hi> This is the ſecond branch. As the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is referred to manifeſt and open violence; ſo this is referred to fraud and deceit.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Caluin ad locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. Cor. 2.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2. Cor. 7.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 Cor. 12.17.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> The word that is here v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, doth ſignifie in the <hi>Originall,</hi> by a couetous deſire to circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uent or defraud a man. And ſo it is vſed in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> applyeth it to the wiles which the Deuill vſeth to beguile the godly withall; <hi>Leſt,</hi> ſayeth he, <hi>we ſhould bee circumuented of Sathan: for we are not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of his enterpriſes.</hi> And in another place, he ſayeth of himſelfe; <hi>Wee haue defrauded no man,</hi> And againe, <hi>Did I make a gaine of you by any of them whom I ſent vnto you? I deſired Titus, &amp; with him I ſent a brother; Did Titus make a gaine of you?</hi> The meaning then of it is this; for a man by couetouſneſſe or other euill meanes, to rayſe his owne benefite out of another mans loſſe.<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note>
            </p>
            <p>From hence we obſerue in the next place, that frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent and deceitfull dealing is a ſinne againſt the will of God, and cannot ſtand with ſanctification. This is confirmed by the teſtimony of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21769:12"/>
where reckoning vp the ſinnes of them that are giuen ouer to a <hi>reprobate ſenſe,</hi> among other things hee ſayth,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.29. 1. Pet. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>they are full of deceit.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> exhorteth all <hi>Chriſtians, to lay aſide all guile and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 101.7.</note> And the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> proteſteth, that hee would not ſuffer a <hi>deceitfull perſon to dwell within his houſe.</hi> This is alſo confirmed by diuers reaſons. Firſt, as was ſaid of the former ſinne: ſo this alſo is againſt nature. And this the heathen man affirmeth;<note n="(a)" place="margin">Cum duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus modis aut vi aut fraude fiat iniuria, fraus quaſi vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peculae, vis Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis videtur, &amp;c. Cic. offic. lib. 3.</note> Seing iniury, ſayth he, is done two wayes, eyther by <hi>force</hi> or by <hi>fraud, fraud</hi> doth as it were, belong to a <hi>Foxe,</hi> and <hi>force</hi> to a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> but both of them are moſt repugnant to the nature of <hi>man;</hi> yet of the two, <hi>fraud</hi> is worthy of greater ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is againſt ciuill ſociety. Man is a ſociable creature. And this is the Law euen of naturall ſociety, that whatſoeuer wee would that men ſhould do to vs, wee bee ready to doe the ſame to them: and on the other ſide,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.12.</note> whatſoeuer wee would not that men ſhould doe to vs, we do not ſo much as offer it to them. Otherwiſe, there can be no commerce, nor trafficke v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongſt men. For, as <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> ſayth well, Becauſe man is a ſociable creature,<note place="margin">2.2 ae. q. art. 3.</note> one man naturally oweth that to another, without which, humane ſociety cannot be preſerued: but men cannot liue and conuerſe together, vnleſſe they may belieue, and truſt one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, as manifeſting the truth one to another.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is a kinde of <hi>theft,</hi> as it is agreede vpon by the moſt Diuines, olde and new. <hi>Hierome</hi> writing vpon that place to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Eph. 4.28.</note> 
               <hi>Let him that stole, ſteale no more, &amp;c.</hi> hath theſe words, Becauſe it is an hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them that are conuerſant in the affairs of this life, though they bee free from other <hi>paſſions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Furtum nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans omne quod alterius damno quaeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> as <hi>fornication, &amp;c.</hi> not to be guilty of <hi>theft:</hi> therefore now he warneth the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that by occaſion of gaine, they incurre not the danger of <hi>theft:</hi> calling that <hi>theft,</hi> whatſoeuer is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21769:12"/>
by another mans loſſe. And <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaid, Shew mee a <hi>lyar,</hi> and a deceitfull perſon,<note place="margin">Ethic. Chriſt. lib. 2.</note> and I will ſhew thee a <hi>thiefe.</hi> And <hi>Danaeus,</hi> If any man, ſayth he by craft or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit procure loſſe and dammage to another, certainely, he is a thiefe.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, it is againſt Chriſtianity, which requireth plaine and open dealing amongſt men. The <hi>heathen O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator</hi> could ſay,<note n="a" place="margin">Inter bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos benè agier oportet &amp; ſine frauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione. Cic. Offic. lib. 3. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Ier. 5.27.</note> Amongſt good and honeſt men, there ſhould be good and honeſt dealing, and without deceit. Much more ſhould they that profeſſe themſelues Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, be thus affected.</p>
            <p>Here then are iuſtly reproued all kinds of fraudulent and deceitfull dealing. A thing ſo common at this day, as wee may ſay with the <hi>Prophet, As a cage is full of birds, ſo are mens houſes full of deceit: thereby they are becom great and waxen rich.</hi> Now there are many kinds of this ſin. I will onely inſiſt in that which is vſed in <hi>contracts,</hi> in <hi>buying and ſelling: Marchants</hi> and <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> haue been of olde condemned generally for couetouſneſſe and bad dealing: <hi>As a nayle in the wall,</hi> ſayth the Wiſe-man,<note place="margin">Eccl. 27, 2.</note> 
               <hi>stic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth faſt betweene the ioynts of the stones: ſo doth ſinne ſticke betweene the ſelling and the buying:</hi> whereupon among the <hi>Hebrues,</hi> a <hi>Marchant</hi> is deriued of a <hi>verbe</hi> that ſignifieth to deceiue. I do not deny, but that <hi>negotiation</hi> and <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> is good in it ſelfe, and very neceſſary for men. For God hath ſo ordered the matter, that as no Country, ſo no man, is ſufficient of himſelfe, but muſt ſupply his wants by buying of another. Hence innumerable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites doe redound to mankind, yea, the whole world almoſt by this meanes is brought into a communion &amp; fellowſhippe. But now the malice of men hath filled it ſo full of deceitfull trickes, that many <hi>Chapmen</hi> are little better then <hi>theeues and robbers.</hi> That which was ſpoken of the followers of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> may bee fitly applyed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that few doe buy and ſell in theſe dayes, that haue not the <hi>marke of the beaſt,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Apoc. 13.17</note> that vſe not lying
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21769:13"/>
and diſſembling. They haue ſo many falſe ſhifts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thoſe that deale with them, that if a man had <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> his eyes, he ſhould hardly ſecure himſelfe from being ouerreached. It is not for nothing, that their trades are called <hi>Myſteries:</hi> for there is a <hi>myſtery of iniquity</hi> in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And <hi>Crafts:</hi> for, as they vſe the matter, there is little but craft and deceit in their dealing:<note n="(a)" place="margin">Qui cauet ne decipiatur, vix cauet, etiam cum cauet, etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum cauiſſe ratus, ſaepe is cautor captus eſt. Plaut. in Captiu.</note> Let a man be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo circumſpect, and looke neuer ſo well to himſelfe, yet it will goe hard, but hee ſhall bee fetched ouer by one tricke or other.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Stobaeus ex Theopompo.</note> It was a cuſtome in <hi>Athens,</hi> that when men bought or ſolde any thing, they came before the <hi>Magistrate</hi> appointed for that purpoſe, and there tooke a ſolemne oath, that they had not dealt fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, nor vſed any cunning or deceit. But it is farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with vs; for both in <hi>buying</hi> &amp; <hi>ſelling,</hi> euery man almoſt,<note place="margin">Mic. 7.2.</note> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſayth, <hi>hunteth his brother with a net.</hi> As it is reported of the fiſh <hi>Polypus,</hi> that when ſhee lyeth in waite for other fiſhes,<note place="margin">Aelian var hiſt. lib. 1. cap. 1.</note> ſhee changeth her colour into the colour of the rocke, and ſo the fiſhes are caught before they be aware, in a net which by nature ſhe hath behind her head, and can ſpread it at her pleaſure. So doe the <hi>Trades men</hi> of theſe dayes, when a man commeth to them, they inſinuate themſelues into him, with the fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and ſmootheſt words that can be deuiſed: but if he take not the better heede, there is a net ſpred to enſnare him, and it will bee hard if he be not caught. But it will be obiected, I compell no man to buy my commodities, I onely ſhew them and make the price: let the <hi>buyer</hi> looke to it.<note place="margin">Caueat emptor</note> But the <hi>Heathen</hi> man will tell thee,<note n="(b)" place="margin">In ſidiae ſunt tendere plagas, etſi excitaturus non ſis nec a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitaturus, &amp;c. Cic. lib. 3. Leu 25.14.</note> that it is bad dealing in thee, to ſpread a net for thy brother, though thou doeſt not hunt him and driue him into it; for the wilde beaſts many times fall into the net that is laid for them, though no man purſue them. The Lord gaue a ſtrait commandement vnto the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that <hi>when they ſolde ought to their neighbor, or bought any thing of their neighbors hand, they ſhould not oppreſſe one another.</hi> But now
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21769:13"/>
there is nothing more common both in <hi>buying &amp; ſelling.</hi> Firſt for <hi>buying.</hi> It is an ordinary practiſe eſpecially with great perſons, that if any of their neighbours haue any commodity that lyeth fit for their vſe, as <hi>Naboths <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> did for <hi>Ahab,</hi> they muſt haue it from him by one meanes or other. If he be vnwilling to part with it, they will ſo weary him with continuall vexations, that hee ſhall bee conſtrained to ſell it whether hee will or no.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ereptio eſt, non emptio, cum venditori ſuo arbitratu vendere non licet. lib. 4. in Ver.</note> But as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaid well, It is rather a taking by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, then a <hi>buying,</hi> when the ſeller may not ſell at his owne choyce. Againe, let a poore man come and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any commodity to ſell, the buyer will preſently take aduantage of his pouerty and neceſſity, and make him ſell it far vnder the worth. To this purpoſe Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> maketh mention of a certaine ieſter, who vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to tel the people, what they all moſt deſired. And when a great multitude were come together, at the time appointed, he ſtood vp, &amp; ſaid with a loud voice,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Vili vultis emere, &amp; charè vendere, de Trinit. lib. 13. cap 3. Prou. 20.14.</note> 
               <hi>You deſire to buy cheape, and ſell deare:</hi> wherunto agreeth that ſaying of <hi>Solomon: It is naught, it is naught, ſayth the buyer, but when hee is gone, hee boaſteth of his penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, in <hi>ſelling,</hi> they haue innumerable deceitfull trickes, and crafty deuiſes, whereby they ſet their owne ſoules to ſale, and that with ſuch ſubtilty, as a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple man ſhall neuer diſcerne them, as though they had <hi>Gyges</hi> his ring, to make them goe inuiſible. So that as the King of <hi>Babel ſacrificed to his net:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.16.</note> ſo may theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to their craft.</p>
            <p>But to touch ſome particulars of their bad dealing. Firſt of all, they offend by lying,<note n="(c)" place="margin">—Plenius aequo laudat vaenales qui vult extrudere merces. Horat. lib. 2. Ep.</note> whiles they ſet a far greater commendation on their wares, then they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue: for ſo they may gaine, though it bee by lying, they care not. They ſing that ſong of <hi>Curio,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Vincat vtilitas. Cic. Offic. lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Let pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite preuaile.</hi> And yet the <hi>heathen</hi> man that neuer knew <hi>God,</hi> hath taught to the ſhame of vs <hi>Christians,</hi> that all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21769:14"/>
lying muſt bee taken from contracts.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if lying will not ſerue the turne, they adde ſwearing and forſwearing, and ſo, as much as in them lyeth, they make God a falſe witneſſe.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Quis metus aut pudor eſt vnquam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantis auari? Iuuen. Sat. 14.</note> For what ſinne ſo haynous, which a couetous wretch, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth haſte to be rich, will be eyther afrayd or aſhamed to commit? They will ſweare it coſt them ſo much, and yet, rather then all fayle, they will ſell it better cheape: they will ſweare they giue you the buying, and they would not ſell it ſo good cheape to another, though they neuer ſaw you before.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they ſinne in inhaunſing and rayſing the price of their commodities aboue meaſure. As the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Amos 8.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>They make the ſhekell great, that they may buy the poore for ſiluer, and the needy for ſhooes.</hi> This is the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of them that ingroſſe a commoditie into their hands when it is cheape, and keepe it vp till it be deare, that ſo they may ſell it at their owne price. The very light of nature hath condemned this ſinne: as the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Orator</hi> putteth this caſe to ſuch perſons;<note place="margin">Offic. lib. 3.</note> namely, If a man, in the time of a great dearth, bring a Ship from beyond Sea laden with corne, and know that there are a great many more Ships comming within a few dayes, if he diſſemble this, and take aduantage of the preſent want, and ſell his corne at too high a rate, hee is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for hard and vniuſt dealing. This poynt is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well determined by <hi>Thomas Aquinas:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. 2 ae. q. 77. art. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Buying</hi> and <hi>Selling</hi> (ſaith hee) was deuiſed for the common good of both parties, and in that reſpect, it ought not to bee a greater grieuance to one then to another: and therfore a contract ought to be made according to the equality of the thing; and that muſt bee meaſured according to the price that is giuen. And therefore, if eyther the price exceede the worth of the thing, or the thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the price, the equalitie of iuſtice is taken away: And therefore, to ſell dearer, or to buy cheaper then
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21769:14"/>
the thing is worth, is in it ſelfe vniuſt and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they offend in ſhewing one thing, and ſelling another. And herein they are their <hi>Craftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masters:</hi> for they haue ſuch cunning conueyance, and ſleight of hand, as a ſimple man cannot ſuſpect, much leſſe diſcerne them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, they ſinne in vſing <hi>falſe waights</hi> and <hi>vniuſt meaſures;</hi> making, as the Prophet ſayth,<note place="margin">Amos. 8.5.</note> 
               <hi>the Ephah as ſmall,</hi> as they make the <hi>ſhekel great.</hi> This is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable in the ſight of God, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayth;<note place="margin">Prou. 11.1.</note> 
               <hi>Falſe ballances are an abomination vnto the Lord.</hi> To this purpoſe, there was a very ſtraite charge in the Law:<note place="margin">Deut. 25 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not haue in thy bagge two manner of waights, a great and a ſmall; neyther ſhalt thou haue in thy houſe diuers meaſures, a great and a ſmall: but thou ſhalt haue a right and iuſt waight:</hi>
               <note place="margin">15.</note> 
               <hi>a perfite and a iuſt meaſure ſhalt thou haue; that thy dayes may bee lengthned in the land, which the Lord thy God giueth thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">16.</note> 
               <hi>for all that do ſuch things, and all that doe vnrighteouſly, are abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto the Lord thy God.</hi> And the Lord ſpeaketh with indignation to the people of <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 6.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>Are yet the treaſures of wickedneſſe in the houſe of the wicked, &amp; the ſcant meaſure that is abominable? Shall I iuſtifie the wicked ballances, and the bagge of deceitfull waights?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, I will not iuſtifie, but condemne them. Beſides, <hi>waights and meaſures</hi> are inſtruments as it were of iuſtice and equity; for thereby things that are vniuſt, ſhould bee reduced vnto equity. And therefore if there bee any iniquity in them, it is ſo much the more diſpleaſing vnto God. And looke how much men take from the iuſt meaſure, ſo much of the wrath and diſpleaſure of God doe they purchaſe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. In a word therfore, let all men remember, what the Lord requireth in this caſe: <hi>Yee ſhall not do vniuſtly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leu. 19.25.36.</note> ſaith he, <hi>in iudgement, in metyard, in waight, or in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21769:15"/>
yee ſhall haue iust balances, true waights, a true Ephah, and a true Hin. I am the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> But if the waights &amp; meaſures be in themſelues neuer ſo right and iuſt, yet if they haue cunning trickes <hi>to falſifie them by deceit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 8.5.</note> that a man cannot haue that hee payeth for, it is all alike odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, they ſinne in ſelling bad and vnprofitable wares in ſtead of good. As the Prophet complaineth of the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 8.6.</note> that they would <hi>ſell the refuſe of the wheate.</hi> It is a lamentable thing to ſee, what baggage ſtuffe <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> and <hi>Chandlers</hi> ſell to poore people, and make them pay as deare as if it were the beſt. And this is the generall complaint concerning <hi>ſale wares,</hi> that men care not how ſleightly it commeth out of their hands: and that there is nothing almoſt made ſo good, and ſo dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as in former times.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, they ſinne in concealing from the buyer, the faults of that they ſell, and ſo ſuffering him to bee deluded.<note place="margin">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae. q. 77. art. 3</note> 
               <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> ſpeaketh very well to this point. It is alwayes vnlawfull, ſaith he, to giue to any man occaſion of loſſe or danger. But the ſeller that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth any thing to ſell, doth herein giue the buyer oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of danger or loſſe, in that he offereth him a thing that is faulty, if by the fault thereof hee incurre danger or loſſe. Loſſe, if for ſuch a fault, the thing that is to bee ſolde, bee leſſe worth, and yet hee for that fault will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate nothing of the price. And danger, if for ſuch a fault the vſe of the thing bee made eyther vnprofitable or hurtfull. As for example, if a man ſell one a lame horſe, for a ſwift running horſe, or a ruinous houſe, for a ſtrong houſe, or corrupted and poyſoned meat, for that which is good. Whereupon, ſaith he, if theſe faults be ſecret &amp; hee doe not diſcouer them, it is vnlawfull and fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſelling, and the ſeller is bound to recompence the loſſe. Yea, this ſinne is exceedingly condemned by the heathen man.<note place="margin">Cic. offic. lib. 3.</note> Who ſeeth not, ſayth hee, what a thing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21769:15"/>
this kind of concealing is, and what a manner of man he is that vſeth it? Surely, he is no plaine dealing man, no honeſt man, no ingenious man, no iuſt, no good man; but rather a ſubtil, a baſe, a fraudulent, a deceitful, a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, a cunning, a ſlie, and a crafty knaue. But the <hi>Chapmen</hi> of theſe dayes are ſo far from making known the faults of the commodities they ſell, as that rather they doe of purpoſe darken their ſhoppes, that the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er cannot ſee what hee buyeth,<note place="margin">Iſa. 59 10.</note> but muſt <hi>grope at noone day, as if it were twilight.</hi> By this practiſe, as one ſayth well, they ſhew themſelues to be the <hi>children of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and their deedes to bee the <hi>deedes of darkeneſſe:</hi> yea they bewray, that they haue a deſire to doe euill, and to deale badly. For, as our <hi>Sauiour</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>Euery man that doeth euill, hateth the light, neyther commeth to the light, leſt his deedes ſhould bee reproued.</hi> And therefore, becauſe <hi>they loue darkeneſſe more then light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">19.</note> let them take heed they heare not that wofull ſentence denounced againſt them, <hi>Binde them hand and foote,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.13.</note> 
               <hi>and caſt them into vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter darkeneſſe, there ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> Theſe are ſome of the vnconſcionable practiſes that are vſed by <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> in <hi>buying</hi> and <hi>ſelling,</hi> and theſe are ſo common at this day, as it is accounted a folly for any man to doe otherwiſe. Euery body will confeſſe, that <hi>plaine dealing is a Iewell,</hi> but they ſay, hee that vſeth it, ſhall die a begger. Yea, they traine vp their ſeruants &amp; <hi>Apprentiſes</hi> to theſe courſes.<note n="a" place="margin">Eò lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilior, quò fraudulentior. Aug. confeſſ. l. 1</note> And if any of them proue more cunning and crafty to ouerreach men that come into their ſhops, then the reſt, hee is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and better accounted of. So that by that time they haue ſerued out their yeares, partly by their owne inbred corruption, and partly by their Maſters ill example,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.15.</note> as our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> ſayde of the <hi>Iewiſh Proſelites,</hi> they become <hi>twofolde more the children of hell,</hi> then their Maſters are. And thus much for the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and the ſeuerall branches thereof. The reaſons follow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21769:16"/>
               <hi>His Brother.)</hi> The firſt reaſon, as hath beene ſayd, is included in this word, <hi>Brother,</hi> and it carrieth great force and waight with it. It was the argument that <hi>Abraham</hi> vſed to <hi>Lot:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>I pray thee let there bee no ſtrife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thee and me, for we are brethren.</hi> And it was the argument that <hi>Moſes</hi> vſed to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> that ſtroue together:<note place="margin">Act. 7.26.</note> 
               <hi>Sirs, yee are brethren, why doe yee wrong one to another?</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. q. 28. art. 3.</note> Now men are called <hi>Brethren,</hi> as <hi>Thomas A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi> obſerueth, foure wayes in the Scriptures: Firſt, by <hi>nature,</hi> and that eyther by <hi>birth,</hi> as <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> borne both of the ſame Parents; or by <hi>bloud,</hi> and ſo all mankinde are brethren:<note place="margin">Act. 17.26.</note> For, as the <hi>Apostle</hi> ſaith; <hi>God made of one bloud all mankinde, to dwell on all the face of the earth.</hi> Secondly, by <hi>Countrey;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calleth the <hi>Iewes</hi> that were his <hi>Countrymen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.3.</note> his <hi>Brethren.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by <hi>Kindred,</hi> as they that come all of one ſtocke or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage: and ſo our <hi>Sauiour Christ</hi> is ſaid to haue brethren and ſiſters; <hi>Is not this the brother of Iames, and Ioſes, and of Iudas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>and Simon? and are not his ſisters here with vs?</hi> And yet wee know that his bleſſed Mother remayned a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin</hi> both before and after his byrth. Fourthly, by <hi>Affection.</hi> I might ſpeake of all theſe, and ſhew the force of the argument in euery one of them: but I will inſiſt onely in the laſt, which is chiefely meant in this place; and indeede it is the ſtrongeſt of all the reſt, and doth moſt of all binde vs to procure the good one of another,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.16. Rom. 12.5. <hi>Doct.</hi>
               </note> it being our coniunction with <hi>Christ</hi> our head, &amp; then in him one with another, wherby we are al made <hi>one body, and euery one one anothers members.</hi> This then doth teach vs, that it is a grieuous ſinne for one <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> to oppreſſe or defraud another. True, it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to offer violence to any man. If there were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, yet euen in this very reſpect, that hee is a <hi>man,</hi> we muſt not doe him any wrong, no though hee were our vtter enemy.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note> As our <hi>Sauiour Christ</hi> ſaith; <hi>Loue your enemies, doe good to them that hate you, &amp;c.</hi> And the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21769:16"/>
               <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorteth; <hi>If thine enemy hunger, feede him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.20, 21</note> 
               <hi>if he thirſt, giue him drinke, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>bee not ouercome of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, but ouercome euill with goodneſſe.</hi> Much leſſe muſt we hurt or harme thoſe that are Chriſtians, of the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion with our ſelues. To this purpoſe there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen bounds ſet downe by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> which, if any thing will preuaile, might ſerue to containe vs in our duety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is one body, and one spirite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.4.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>euen as yee are called in one hope of your vocation. There is one Lord, one faith, one Baptiſme, one God and Father of all.</hi> There is <hi>one body.</hi> As in the <hi>naturall body,</hi> there is no member more for it ſelfe, then for the whole; ſo it ſhould bee in this <hi>mysticall body:</hi> Thoſe that are, as it were, eyes and hands, muſt not oppreſſe the feet. There is <hi>one spirite,</hi> which is, as it were, a ſoule in this body, which knitteth all the members thereof a great deale nearer, then the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the naturall body are coupled with ioynts and ſinewes. There is <hi>one hope of our calling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.16.</note> whereby wee are called to an inheritance in the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. There is <hi>one Lord,</hi> whoſe ſeruants wee all profeſſe our ſelues to be. And therefore, as they that ſerue one Maſter, and liue in one houſe, ought not to wrong one another: no more ſhould wee that would bee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of <hi>Gods houſhold,</hi> offer iniury to our <hi>fellow ſeruants.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.49.</note> There is <hi>one faith,</hi> whereby wee belieue the ſame graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes of God for our comfort. There is one <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> wherein wee all promiſed before the <hi>God</hi> of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, before <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> to renounce all the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed deedes of darkenes. Laſt of all, there is <hi>one God the Father of vs all,</hi> not onely by <hi>creation,</hi> as hee is alſo of the wicked and vnreaſonable creatures (in which reſpect <hi>Iob</hi> calleth the crawling <hi>wormes his ſiſters;</hi>) but chiefly,<note place="margin">Iob. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>by grace and regeneration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quae ſi non proſunt ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, multa iuua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> and wee all would bee reputed his <hi>children.</hi> There is neuer a one of theſe bonds, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſingle by it ſelfe, it might bee of force to tye vs to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21769:17"/>
the good behauiour towards our brethren: but all of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laide together, cannot chufe, if there bee any ſparke of grace, but mightily preuaile with vs.</p>
            <p>And therefore, to apply this in a word, it ſerueth to reproue thoſe that breake all theſe bonds. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>a threefold corde is not eaſily broken.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 4.12.2.</note> But here is a greater corde; here are firſt, as we haue heard, foure arguments of <hi>brotherhood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.4.</note> then, here are <hi>ſeuen bonds of loue,</hi> to tie and vnite vs in affection one towards another. And yet all theſe are not ſtrong enough. There are a number of <hi>falſe brethren</hi> in all the former reſpects.<note place="margin">Gal. 2.4.</note> And it is hard to finde any in this age,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.8.</note> that will not <hi>doe wrong, and do harm euen to their brethren.</hi> So that as the Prophet ſayth, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man muſt take heed of his neighbour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>and not truſt in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brother: for euery brother will vſe deceit, and euery friend will deale deceitfully: and euery one will deceiue his friend, and will not speake the truth: for they haue taught their tongues to speake lies, &amp;c.</hi> Yea, many are growne to that paſſe, that they will deceiue their owne fathers. The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred profeſſion of <hi>religion,</hi> which ought to bee the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of all bonds, that heauen and earth can affoorde, is violated and troden vnder foote. Yea, it is too euident, that there are many, that vſe their profeſſion <hi>for a cloake of maliciouſneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.16. Gal. 5.13.</note> They thinke that men will the ſooner belieue and credite them fot their profeſſion ſake, and ſo by that meanes they doe the more dangerouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. And hereby it commeth to paſſe, that the mouths of profane perſons are opened againſt them, and the holy <hi>name</hi> &amp; <hi>Gospell</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is diſgraced: for indeed there can no greater reproch redound to the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> then when they that are the profeſſors of it, make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of their dealing. According to that ſpeech of the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">Rom. 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>The name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles through you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.14.</note> And ſo <hi>Nathan</hi> tolde <hi>Dauid,</hi> that by that wicked deed of his, <hi>hee had cauſed the enemies of God to blaspheme.</hi> For this is the property of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21769:17"/>
that whatſoeuer they can finde amiſſe in a man that profeſſeth <hi>religion,</hi> preſently they impute it to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and to the <hi>religion</hi> it ſelfe. And hence it is, that <hi>Papiſts</hi> on the one ſide, and <hi>Atheiſts</hi> on the other ſide, doe exclame againſt vs. Theſe are your profeſſors, theſe are your Bible-bearers, theſe are they that will not miſſe a Sermon, and yet they will diſſemble as deepely, &amp; vſe as much bad dealing as other men. And doubtleſſe, this is that which diſgraceth this famous City; that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the <hi>Gospell</hi> ſo plentifully as they haue, and making ſuch a <hi>profeſſion</hi> of <hi>religion</hi> as generally they do, yet there is ſo little conſcience and equity in their dealing. And therefore, let them be exhorted in the feare of <hi>God,</hi> to walke anſwerably to their profeſſion, that ſo, as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> ſayth, <hi>They may take away occaſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.12.</note> 
               <hi>from them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire occaſion against them.</hi> There is nothing in the world that ought to bee ſo deare vnto a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> man, no not his owne life, as the credite of the <hi>Gospell.</hi> And therefore, as wee tender it, and would bee loth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to contempt, by the ſlanderous reproaches of wicked men; let vs make conſcience of our wayes; that they that <hi>speake euill of vs, as of euill doers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, when they ſhall ſee our good conuerſation in Chriſt.</hi> And thus much ſhall ſuffice briefly to haue ſpoken of the firſt reaſon, in this word <hi>Brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Lord is the auenger of all ſuch.)</hi> This is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reaſon, which is plainely expreſſed. And it is taken from the vengeance of <hi>God,</hi> that they that will not bee drawne by loue, may be forced by feare. And it is added by due order to that which is ſupplyed out of the third verſe; namely, <hi>It is the will of God, that no man oppreſſe or defraud his brother:</hi> for the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of <hi>God</hi> doth alwayes follow the violating of his will. Now it is to bee obſerued, that the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> doth vſe here the <hi>preſent time:</hi> becauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> not onely will bee, but alſo hath beene in all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21769:18"/>
of the world, and ſtill is at this day, the auenger of all ſuch things.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Doctrine.</note>From hence wee learne, that the Lord will moſt ſurely puniſh all oppreſſion and fraudulent dealing, and all iniury that a man doth to his neighbour.<note place="margin">Prou. 22.22.23</note> The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is plentiful in the proofe of this point. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rob not the poore, becauſe hee is poore, &amp;c. For the Lord will defend their cauſe, and spoyle the ſoule of thoſe that ſpoyle them.</hi> And the Lord gaue a ſtrict charge to the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and inforced it with a ſeuere threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:<note place="margin">Exod. 22.22.23.24.</note> 
               <hi>Yee ſhall not trouble any widdow nor fatherleſſe child. If thou vexe or trouble any ſuch, and ſo he call and cry vnto me, I will ſurely heare his cry. Then ſhall my wrath bee kindled, and I will kill you with the ſword, and your wiues ſhall be widdowes, and your children fatherleſſe.</hi> Where wee ſee, that the Lord will pay them home in their owne kinde. And to this purpoſe ſaith the <hi>Prophet Dauid;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 12.5.</note> 
               <hi>Now for the oppreſſion of the needy, and for the ſighes of the poore, I will vp,</hi> ſayth the Lord, <hi>and will ſet at liberty him whom the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hath ſnared.</hi>
               <note place="margin">&amp; 10.14</note> And in another place; <hi>Thou beholdeſt miſchiefe and wrong, that thou mayest take the matter into thy hands: the poore committeth himſelfe vnto thee: for thou art the helper of the fatherleſſe.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teſtifyeth, that it is a <hi>righteous thing with God, to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence tribulation to them that trouble you.</hi> With men many times they are not puniſhed,<note place="margin">Dat veniam coruis, vexat cenſura colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas, Iuu. ſat. 2. Cic. in Ver. l. 3. Col 4.1.</note> the law taketh little holde of them. They breake through the lawes, as great flies doe through the cobwebbes: yea, ſuch is their power &amp; might, that no man dare call them into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; yea, men had rather indure any thing, then complayne of their wrong and iniuries. But GOD who is moſt iuſt, will reuenge all iniuſtice: as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayth to earthly Maſters; <hi>Yee Maſters, doe vnto your ſeruants that which is iust and equall, knowing that yee alſo haue a Master in heauen.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Quicquid à vobis minor extimeſcit, Maior hoc vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis dominus minatur. Sen in Thyeſte</note> So it may be ſayd to all great perſons; See yee offer no violence to thoſe that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21769:18"/>
are vnder you, for there is a greater then you in heauen. According to that ſpeech of <hi>Solomon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>Romooue not the ancient bounds, and enter not into the fields of the fatherleſſe: For hee that redeemeth them, is mighty, he will defend their cauſe against thee.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Non di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulat iniuriam filii Pater. De aduent. Dom. Serm. 1. Ecclus. 35.15.</note> A Father (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) will not diſſemble the iniury that is done to his childe: Much leſſe will our heauenly Father put vp the wrongs that are done to his children. <hi>Doe not the teares runne downe the widdowes cheekes?</hi> (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>and her cry is against him that cauſed them: from her cheekes doe they goe vp vnto heauen, and the Lord which heareth them, doth accept them.</hi> There is neuer a teare, which cruel <hi>Tyrants</hi> wring from the eyes of the poore,<note place="margin">Pſal. 56.8. &amp; 58.11.</note> but the Lord <hi>putteth it into his bottle,</hi> and in the end he will make it appeare, that there is a <hi>God that iudgeth the earth.</hi> But not to dwell thus in the generall, let vs ſee how and by what meanes the <hi>Lord</hi> doth reuenge them: ſurely the Lord hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes euen in this life to take vengeance of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours and wrongfull dealers. And firſt of all, by the curſes of the people that are oppreſſed by them: For if <hi>the people will curſe him that withdraweth his owne corne</hi> in the time of dearth;<note place="margin">Pro. 11.26.</note> much more they that by oppreſſion take corne from the poore, ſhal bring many a bitter and heauy curſe vpon themſelues: but it may be they paſſe not much for this; <hi>The Foxe fareth best when he is curſed.</hi> Therefore the Lord doth puniſh them with infamy and diſgrace, that their very <hi>names doe rot</hi> and ſtinke.<note place="margin">Pro. 10.7.</note> Their cruell and vnconſcionable dealing openeth all mens mouthes againſt them, and maketh euery body cry out on them: it may be, not to their faces, for it is like, they haue <hi>trencher ſlaues</hi> ynow that flatter them,<note place="margin">Turpe eſt monſtrari di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gito &amp; dicter hic eſt.</note> and extoll them to the sky: but they cannot walke in the ſtreetes, no nor ride in their Coaches, but they are poynted at, and rayled vpon. But it may be they care not much for this neyther, but rather doe boaſt themſelues and glory in it;<note n="b" place="margin">Quid enim ſaluis infamia nummis? In. ſat. 1.</note> For what is diſgrace, ſo long as a man hath his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21769:19"/>
bags full of money? He can ſing with that old Churle in the <hi>Poet:</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Populus me ſibilat, at mihi plaudo Ipſe domi, ſimulac nummos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plor in arca, Horat. lib. 1. ſat. 1. Gen. 41.20, 21. Iob. 20.15.19.</note> The people hiſſeth at mee abroad, but when I come home, and ſee my coffers full of coyne, I can applaude and make much of my ſelfe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord doth puniſh them ſometimes with pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: that as thoſe <hi>ſeuen leane kine,</hi> which <hi>Pharaoh</hi> drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of, did eate vp the <hi>ſeuen fat kine,</hi> and yet <hi>were neyther fuller nor fatter:</hi> So, though thoſe great oppreſſours, by vndoing many, <hi>deuoure much ſubſtance:</hi> yet, by the iuſt hand of God vpon them, many times they are neuer the richer. And this the Lord threatneth by the <hi>Prophet,</hi> ſaying;<note place="margin">Iſa. 33.1.</note> 
               <hi>Woe be to thee that ſpoylest, and wast not ſpoyled, &amp;c. When thou ſhalt ceaſe to ſpoyle, thou ſhalt be ſpoiled: when thou ſhalt make an end of doing wickedly, they ſhall doe wickedly against thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2.7, 8.</note> And in another place: As in the Sea one fiſh deuoureth another, and a greater commeth after and deuoureth them both: So many times it commeth to paſſe, that they which take delight in ſpoiling others, become a prey to ſome that are mightier then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And this commonly befalleth them who haue beene inſtruments of oppreſſion vnto other men, who in the end deale with them,<note place="margin">Sueton. in eius vita.</note> as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpaſian</hi> did with his Officers; he vſed them as <hi>ſpunges</hi> to ſucke vp the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the poore, and when they were full, he cruſhed them out into his owne veſſels. So true is that ſaying;<note n="b" place="margin">Non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet euentus ſordida praeda bonos, Ouid. Amor.</note> Baſely gotten gayne neuer commeth to good.</p>
            <p>Sometimes the Lord puniſheth them with barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that they goe childleſſe to their graues, and though they gather a deale of wealth together by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable courſes, yet they haue no heyre to leaue it to when they haue done.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> hath a ſaying to this purpoſe: <hi>There is one alone which hath neyther ſonne nor brother, yet is there no end of all his trauell, neyther can his eye be ſatisfied with riches, neyther doth he thinke, For whom doe I trauell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39, 6.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith; <hi>He diſquieteth himſelfe in vaine, he heapeth vp riches, and cannot tell who ſhall gather them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21769:19"/>Sometimes the Lord taketh them away by vntimely death. As <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth;<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.23.</note> 
               <hi>The bloud-thirsty and deceitfull men ſhall not liue out halfe their dayes.</hi> And hereof wee haue experience (as alſo of the former;) for wee ſee many of theſe vnconſcionable perſons, that care not how they oppreſſe and defraud others to inrich themſelues, <hi>Die in their full ſtrength,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Iob. 21.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>when their brests are full of milke, and their bones runne full of marrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes they are puniſhed with a reprochful and ignominious death, the poore people inſulting ouer them, as once they did ouer the King of <hi>Babel</hi> when he was dead: <hi>They tooke vp this Prouerbe againſt him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 14, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>and ſaid; How hath the oppreſſor ceaſed! and the gold-thirsty Babel rested! The Lord hath broken the rodde of the wicked, and the ſcepter of the rulers, &amp;c.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">7.10, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>The world is at reſt, and is quiet, they ſing for ioy.</hi> And a little after; <hi>They cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſayde vnto him, Art thou alſo become weake as we? art thou become like vnto vs? &amp;c.</hi> It is like they ſhall be buried with great ſtate, and ſome clawbacke or other, in a <hi>funerall ſermon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 32, 5.</note> will not ſticke to commend them aboue meaſure, &amp; to <hi>call the niggard liberall, &amp; the churle bountifull:</hi> but in the meane while, the people will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride them. And which is worſt of all, though as the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Ezech. 32, 27.</note> 
               <hi>They goe downe to the graue with their weapons of warre, &amp;c. yet their iniquity and their oppreſſion is in their bones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Somtimes they are puniſhed in their poſterity, which for the moſt part come to beggery. There is a fearefull ſaying in the Propheſie of <hi>Nahum. The Lion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nahum. 2, 12, 13.</note> ſayth the Prophet, <hi>did teare in peeces enough for his whelpes, and worried</hi> for his <hi>Lioneſſe, and filled his holes with prey, &amp; his dennes with spoyle.</hi> But marke what followeth: <hi>Behold, I come vnto thee,</hi> ſayth the Lord, <hi>and I will burn her charrets in the ſmoake, and the ſword ſhall deuoure the young Lions, &amp; I will cut off thy spoyle from the earth, &amp;c.</hi> wherby we ſee, that though great men, like Lions, ſpoyle and deuoure
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21769:20"/>
on euery ſide, yet their children ſhall be little better for it.<note place="margin">Iob. 27.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14.</note> According to that which <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith; <hi>This is the portion of a wicked man with God, and the heritage of tyrants which they ſhall receiue of the Almighty: If his children be in great number, the ſword ſhall deſtroy them, and his poſterity ſhall not be ſatisfied with bread.</hi> But it is worthy our obſeruation, to conſider what means the Lord in his prouidence vſeth to bring this to paſſe. Many times hee taketh away the couetous father, before his ſonne and heyre come to age, at leaſt before hee come to diſcretion to mannage his eſtate; and then my young Maſter laſheth it out, and can ſtand on no ground,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Quodcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que profunda Traxit auaritia luxu peiore refundit. Claudian.</note> till with a forke he haue caſt abroad al that his father gathered together with a rake. We need not goe farre for inſtances in this caſe. There hath been ſufficient experience of it in this City. Haue not your eyes ſeene mountaines of wealth, heaped vp by vniuſt courſes, ſodenly thawed away like yce before the ſunne, and melted like waxe, when it hath felte the heate of the fire? And this is that which is ſpoken in our common Prouerbe;<note place="margin">Malê parta, malê dilabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> 
               <hi>Euill gotten goods are euill spent.</hi> Nay a ſmall thing that is euill gotten, will by the iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God proue a <hi>canker,</hi> to waſte and conſume a great deale that is well gotten.<note place="margin">Rarò gaudebit tertius haeres.</note> And though peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, this proue not true in the firſt heire, yet ſuch goods doe ſeldome continue to the third generation.</p>
            <p>Another puniſhment that God inflicteth vpon ſuch perſons, is this, that their prayers are not heard. As the Lord himſelfe threatneth them:<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>Though yee make many prayers, I will not heare, becauſe your hands are full of bloud.</hi> And <hi>Sirach</hi> ſayth well to this purpoſe;<note place="margin">Eccl. 34.25.</note> 
               <hi>When one prayeth, and another curſeth, whoſe voyce will the Lord heare?</hi> How then can they looke to haue their prayers heard, when a great number of thoſe whom they haue oppreſſed, doe cry for vengeance againſt them? If a man ſhould come before an earthly Iudge to craue fauour for himſelfe, &amp; a multitude of poore men, with their wiues and children
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21769:20"/>
ſhould fall on their knees before the Iudge, &amp; complain what wrong and iniuries he hath done vnto them, the iudge would neuer reſpect him; much leſſe can ſuch perſons looke for any fauour at Gods hand, ſo long as the cry of the oppreſſed is in his eares.</p>
            <p>Sometimes they are puniſhed with a guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as one ſayth well, They haue gaine in their cofers;<note place="margin">Lucrum in arca, damnum in conſcientia, &amp;c. Rom. 2.5.</note> but loſſe in their conſcience; yea gaine that is vniuſtly come by, is a wofull treaſury. Such perſons doe <hi>treaſure vp to themſelues wrath against the day of wrath, &amp;c.</hi> Euery penny that is hoorded vp by ſinnefull courſes, will bring with it in the end a pound of horror of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Theſe are the puniſhments wherewith God ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vengeance on oppreſſors and fraudulent perſons in this life. And though it ſhould fall out, that they ſhould eſcape all theſe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.9.10.</note> yet there is a farre worſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life; and that is, they ſhall for euer bee exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of the Kingdome of heauen. And therefore let mee vſe that exhortation of the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto them; <hi>O conſider this, you that forget God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.22.</note> 
               <hi>leſt he teare you in peeces, and there be none to deliuer you:</hi> For as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Heb. 10.31.</note> 
               <hi>It is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may bee they will obiect: They hope to doe well inough for all this; They will doe ſome deedes of Charity when they die: they will build an <hi>Hospitall</hi> or an <hi>Almes houſe,</hi> or ſome way or other relieue the poore, and that ſhall make amends for all. But let all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons know, that the <hi>Prophet</hi> maketh this a ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of a godly man, <hi>to giue his own bread to the hungry.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 13.7.</note> Vpon which place <hi>Hierom</hi> wel obſerueth, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet doth ſufficiently ſay, his own bread, leſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould turne bread gotten by oppreſſion and vſury, into a work of mercy; As wee ſee many doe, ſayth he, who oppreſſe by their power, or commit theft, that of much they may giue a little to the poore; and the Miniſter may make
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21769:21"/>
mention of their names among the benefactors. They pleaſe themſelues in the applauſe of the people, when their conſcience ſtingeth and vexeth them within. I do not deny, but the poore may be much relieued &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted by this means: but whether it will be acceptable to God or no, that is the queſtion <hi>Barnard</hi> hath a ſweet ſaying to this purpoſe:<note n="(a)" place="margin">Non rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit Eleemoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas de manu raptoris aut foeneratoris. Credo non redolebant lilia manus illae; &amp; propte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea reſpuebat munus exillis, qui paſci inter lilia conſueuit, &amp; non inter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpinas in Cant. Serm. 71.</note> God receyueth not, ſaith hee, any almes at the hands of an oppreſſor, or an vſurer; I thinke his hands do not ſmell of lilies, but of thorns, and therefore hee refuſed to take a gift from them, who feedeth among the lilies, and not among the thornes. Yea <hi>Plinius Secundus,</hi> though an <hi>heathen</hi> man, ſpeaketh very grauely concerning this point.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pauperes non vt ferarum catuli ſanguine &amp; caedibus muriendi: quodque gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimum eſt accipientibus, ſcient dari ſibi quod nemini eſt ereptum. Paneggyr. ad Traianum. Prou. 3.9. Epheſ. 4.28.</note> The poore, ſaith he, are not to be fed like the whelpes of wilde beaſts, with bloud and murther. But then is a gift moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them that receiue it, when they know that that which is giuen to them, is not taken from ſome body els. VVhen a man ſhall thinke, this meat that I eate, was taken out of the mouthes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fatherleſſe children: this gowne or this apparrell that I weare, was taken from the backs of the poore: and hee that prouided this harbour and lodging for mee, turned many poore people out of dores, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee ſo comfortable vnto him as otherwiſe it would. And therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> exhorteth men to <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Lord,</hi> but, <hi>with their owne riches.</hi> And the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle</hi> would haue men to <hi>leaue stealing, and to worke with their hands the thing that is good, that they may haue to giue to him that needeth.</hi> That that is giuen to the poore, muſt not bee gotten by vnlawfull means, but by honeſt labour: for as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth well,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Quale eſt illud munus quod alter cum gaudio accipit, alter cum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit?</note> What a manner of gift is that, which one receyueth with ioy, and another loſeth with griefe? When <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> made prouiſion for building the Temple, and ſaw how chearefully the Princes offered thereunto, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a ſolemn thankſgiuing to God, &amp; acknowledgeth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21769:21"/>
that they had firſt receiued all from God.<note place="margin">1. Chr. 29.14.</note> 
               <hi>Of thine owne hand,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>haue wee giuen thee.</hi> That which men giue to God, they muſt firſt receiue of Gods hand, and not of the deuils hand. For if it be vniuſtly gotten, it is ſo farre from pacifying, as it will rather prouoke the wrath of GOD againſt them,<note place="margin">Luc. 19.8.</note> vnleſſe with good <hi>Zacheus</hi> they firſt make reſtitution. And therefore to conclude this point; let mee ſay vnto them, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> ſayde to the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>Let my counſell bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto them, let them breake off their ſinnes by righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As wee haue tolde you before &amp; testified.)</hi> This latter reaſon is confirmed by the <hi>Apostles</hi> former teſtimony; he had before ſeriouſly reproued them for theſe ſins, &amp; had denounced the iudgements of God againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this conſtancy of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> we that are the <hi>Ministers</hi> of the Word, are taught, that we muſt not coldly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſly reproue mens ſins, but oppoſe the threatnings of the Word, &amp; the vengeance of God againſt them.<note place="margin">Iſa. 58.1.</note> This the Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah; Cry aloud, spare not, lift vp thy voyce like a trumpet, &amp; ſhew my people their tranſgreſſion, &amp; the houſe of Iacob their ſins. Ministers</hi> muſt be (as <hi>Christ</hi> called <hi>Iames</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn) Boanerges,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Mar. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>the ſons of thunder:</hi> they muſt thunder and lighten againſt vngodlneſſe and ſinne. And therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth <hi>Timotheus</hi> a ſtrait charge,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.2.</note> that in preaching of the Word, <hi>he improue, rebuke, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.15.</note> And he commandeth <hi>Titus</hi> to <hi>rebuke with all authority.</hi> And againe, he ſayth to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motheus, Them that ſinne, rebuke openly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>that the reſt may feare.</hi> The reaſon is euident. For ſuch is the dulnes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nature, that of themſelues they are not affected with any ſenſe of Gods iudgements: yea they are ſo blinded with ſelfe loue, &amp; ſo hardned with the deceitfulnes of ſinne, that willingly they wil not acknowledge themſelues to be ſinners. And therefore, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> muſt pull the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard from their faces, and hold the glaſſe of <hi>Gods</hi> lavv
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21769:22"/>
before them whether they will or no, that ſo they may ſee their ſinnes, and the vengeance due vnto them. Thus did the <hi>Prophet Nathan</hi> with <hi>Dauid,</hi> when hee lay in his ſin for a time without repentance; he telleth him plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art the man,</hi> thus and thus hath <hi>God</hi> bleſſed thee, and thus and thus haſt thou rewarded him; &amp; therefore thus and thus will the Lord be reuenged of thee. And thus did the <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> with thoſe ſecure &amp; careles <hi>Iewes,</hi> who for the ſpace of fifty dayes were not ſo much as once touched for their ſin; he laboureth to conuince their conſciences, that they had imbrued their hands in the bloud of the ſonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This doctrine hath a twofold vſe. Firſt, it ſerueth to reproue thoſe flattering <hi>Ministers,</hi> who onely preach <hi>pleaſing and ſmooth things</hi> vnto the people,<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.10.</note> and ſing them <hi>a ſong of mercy</hi> onely, without any mention of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; <hi>who ſow pillowes vnder mens arme-boles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 13.18.</note> as the Prophet ſpeaketh, to make them ſleepe more ſecurely in their ſins.<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 2.5.</note> The <hi>Apostle Paul</hi> tooke another courſe with this people; for he taketh themſelues to witneſſe, that <hi>hee neuer vſed flattering words.</hi> And ſpeaking of the abuſes &amp; corruptions, which the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had brought into the <hi>Lords Supper:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.22.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhall I ſay to you</hi> ſayth he, <hi>ſhal I praiſe you in this?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stapleton Domini. in 3. quadrageſ.</note> 
               <hi>I prayſe you not:</hi> whereupon, one, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe none of the beſt, ſayde very well; They are Miniſters of Satan, that dare promiſe peace to a wicked man without repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And it is the greateſt deceiuing that can be, to ſecure a man that liueth in the ſtate of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it ſerueth to reproue all ſuch hearers of the word, as cannot endure that the <hi>Miniſter</hi> ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce threatnings of Gods iudgements againſt their ſinnes.<note place="margin">Ezech. 13.10. Ier. 6.14.15.</note> So long as the <hi>Miniſter</hi> doth <hi>daube with vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered morter,</hi> ſo long as he will <hi>heale their hurt with ſweet words,</hi> and ſtroke their head in their ſinnes, ſo long as hee will not open his mouth againſt their ſinnes, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21769:22"/>
will giue them a <hi>placarde</hi> to continue in them; yea it may be, wil <hi>runne with them to the ſame exerciſe of ryot;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4, 4.</note> hee is a Preacher for their tooth, then they loue him &amp; commend him: but if in conſcience of his duety, hee will <hi>rebuke them ſharpely, and not ſuffer them to ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leu 19.17.</note> then they cry out of him, as they did of the <hi>Prophet Ieremy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15, 10.</note> to be a <hi>contentions man, and a man that striueth with the whole earth.</hi> Thus did <hi>Abab</hi> with <hi>Michaiah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 22, 8.</note> 
               <hi>There is</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>another Prophet, but I hate him, for hee doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie good vnto me, but euill.</hi> I can neuer heare him, but he vexeth me; he is alwayes telling me of my ſinnes. And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayth, that the <hi>Galatians</hi> accounted him their <hi>enemie, becauſe hee tolde them the truth.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">Gal. 4, 16.</note> if it be poſſible, they will finde ſome cauill or other againſt their doctrine, that ſo they may accuſe them as enemies to the State. As <hi>Amaſiah</hi> that falſe Prophet complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of <hi>Amos,</hi> that hee had <hi>conſpired against the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 7, 10.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; that the land was not able to beare his words.</hi> And if their words will ſerue, hee ſhall hardly eſcape without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. As <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> when the <hi>Prophet</hi> threatned <hi>Gods</hi> iudgements againſt him for his <hi>idolatry,</hi> hee cryed,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 13, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Lay holde on him.</hi> And <hi>Amaſiah</hi> ſayde to another Prophet in the like caſe, <hi>Haue they made thee the Kings Counſeller? ceaſe, why ſhould they ſmite thee?</hi> But this is a more grieuous ſinne, then men are aware of. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Prou. 29, 1.</note> 
               <hi>A man that hardneth his necke when hee is rebuked, ſhall ſuddenly bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and cannot be cured.</hi> And doubtleſſe, the time wil come, that they ſhall curſe the time, that euer they gaue credite to flattering Preachers. As the <hi>Church</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the <hi>Lamentations, Thy Prophets haue looked out vaine and fooliſh things for thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lament. 2, 14.</note> 
               <hi>they haue not diſcouered thine iniquity, to turne away thy captiuity, &amp;c.</hi> Confeſſing, that if their Prophets had dealt ſincerely with them, and brought them to the ſight of their ſinnes, they had repented of them, and ſo had not gone into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity. Nay, it is the greateſt token of <hi>Gods</hi> anger that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21769:23"/>
can be, when he ſendeth ſuch <hi>clawbacke Miniſters</hi> vnto a people.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 9.7.</note> As the <hi>Prophet</hi> plainely ſheweth; <hi>The dayes of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are come, the dayes of recompence are come; Iſrael ſhall know it.</hi> And becauſe the people might obiect; Our Prophets tell vs otherwiſe, they perſwade vs, that <hi>God</hi> is a mercifull <hi>God,</hi> and that hauing ſet his loue vpon vs, to make vs his peculiar people, hee will not thus reiect and caſt vs off: Therefore the Prophet meeteth with them in the next words, Doth <hi>your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanch. in locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> ſayth he, tell you ſo? then <hi>the Prophet is a foole, and the man of the spirit,</hi> (that is, the falſe Prophet, that boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth he hath the ſpirit of God, and that hee ſpeaketh by it) <hi>is mad.</hi> And whereas they might obiect further, Why then doth the Lord ſend vs ſuch Prophets? He anſwereth, <hi>that for the multitude of their iniquities, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the hatred of God is great againſt them.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.22.</note> to ſhut vp all in a word, let vs be perſwaded <hi>to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the words of exhortation.</hi> And howſoeuer it may bee harſh and vnpleaſing at the firſt, yet if euer it pleaſe God to bring vs to repentance, then as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Pro. 28.23.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that rebuketh a man, ſhall finde more fauour at the laſt, then hee that flattereth with his tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
